Guide to the Montana State Board of Hail Insurance Records 1917-1991
Montana Historical Society
Montana State Board Of Hail Insurance Records
1917-1991
Montana Historical Society Archives
RS 63
Montana State Board of Hail Insurance
22 linear feet of shelf space
These Montana State Board of Hail Insurance records consist of minutes (1917-1983); abstracts (1917-1986) of hail insurance policies; hail loss records (1917-1991); hail insurance delinquencies (1917-1932); cumulative recapitulations; and a report (1951) on the operations of the State Hail Insurance Fund, administered by the Board.
The Montana State Board of Hail Insurance was established under SB 16 by the 1917 legislature. The Board was composed of the State Auditor, the Commissioner of Agriculture and Publicity, and three members to be appointed by the Governor from a list submitted by the various organized farmers' societies. The law, however, did not appropriate funds for the Board, instead providing that operating funds would be deducted out of insurance premiums collected along with November taxes. This meant there was no money for the Board to begin functioning. Attorney General Samuel Ford advised the Board to begin operation without funds while waiting a decision on the constitutionality of the law. The Board got over this initial hurdle and has provided the state's farmers with low cost hail insurance over since.
Records consist of minutes (April 1917-October 1983) of State Board of Hail Insurance meetings; abstracts (1917-1986) of hail insurance policies; hail insurance delinquencies (1917-1932); hail loss records (1917-1991); cumulative recapitulations (1917-1963); and a report (1951) on the operation of the State Hail Insurance Fund, administered by the Board.
The collection is arranged by series.
Collection open for research.
Acquisition information is available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings in the Montana Historical Society Archives catalog. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Hail--Montana; Insurance, Hail--Montana
Montana; Government and Politics
Detailed Description of the Collection
The following section contains a detailed listing of the materials in the collection
- Financial Records
  - Abstract of hail insurance policies, 1917-1961 (Volume Vol. 1-18)
  - Abstract of hail insurance policies, 1962-1983 (Box-folder OvFd / 1-11)
  - Abstract of hail insurance policies, 1984-1986 (Volume Vol. 19)
  - Hail insurance delinquencies, 1917-1932 (Volume Vol. 20-23)
  - Hail loss record, 1917-1966 (Volume Vol. 24-31)
  - Hail loss record, 1967-1979 (Box-folder OvFd / 12-14)
  - Hail loss record, 1980-1986 (Volume Vol. 32)
  - Hail loss record, 1987-1991 (Box-folder 1 / 1-5)
  - Risk, levy, and losses, by county, annual and cumulative recapitulation, 1917-1963 (Box-folder 2 / 1)
  - Risk, levy, and losses, by grain, annual and cumulative recapitulation, 1919-1963 (Box-folder 2 / 2-3)
- Minutes
  - Minutes, 1917 April-1948 December (Box-folder 3 / 1-2)
  - Minutes, 1949 June-1963 October (Box-folder 4 / 1-3)
- Reports
  - Preliminary report on the operation of the State Hail Insurance Fund, 1951 (Box-folder 4 / 4)